oh
okay the blue button touch the blue
button there you go hello hello Doan
hello and I'm going to take the
recording back off just
so well welcome to this Mastermind on
y21 days and how we can learn to live
with the defects that we may have been
born with now I had prepared to
share ah and I don't think I can get
that done on the phone that I'm
recording on right now but I had
prepared to show you
a a student that a colleague of mine
accepted into her class who was born
without arms and legs and became this
Fant fantastic speaker and author and um
yeah so as an example to show you that
of course we can always make the most of
what we have and not let
physical
hindrances stop us from following our
purpose or finding our Purpose with
those those limitations that may be
imposed because of physical limitations
now a minute as to where I am sitting
right now in a way also with limitations
um because I am in transition in my
friends Garden cottage which is an
unfinished little cottage and with very
limited
facilities and
therefore um I had to get a portable
system to even be online but all of that
is possible but we adjust to the given
circumstances right so that's where I am
right now I just took some sunshine
outside in this beautiful yard um I
should really show you ah no I don't
want to jinx it um and turn the camera
around so
here we are I'm in transition to getting
my next house that I bought um renovated
and finished and
hopefully in a few weeks I will be in
that house and everything will be much
more settled but maybe this is a good
moment to talk about living with the
limitations that are imposed upon us and
that we can't change and still still
living to that high level of purpose and
joyfulness
and yeah enjoying all these different
challenges that come with limitations as
well
so 21 days is also a course that I give
and in these 21 days you know there's
been a lot of talk and then there's been
rebuttal about it doesn't really work in
21 days that 21 days is the average
period that it takes to change habits
that it takes to settle into new
behavior and be comfortable with it of
course I feel very often I adjust much
faster but other people will also say no
it takes much longer to adjust to a new
lifestyle or create a new routine and
really make it settle in so that it
works
um all the time more or
less uh that's why the 21 days goes
along with this realization that we all
have limitations and that nevertheless
we can be
enormously productive and meaningfully
contribute to the world and our
community never mind what kind of
limitations we
have
so even though I cannot show you the
clip the YouTube clip that I wanted to
show you maybe I'll edit it in later I
want to quickly go about talk
about um jannis
mcdavis jannis mcdavis
was admitted into my colleagues first
grade or I think second grade she took
the class over in second grade
um class even though other teachers had
advised her against it and this was at
the time when I was completing my um
degree in waldor
education and ASD is her name and I were
close friends and had a lot of these
Forward Thinking what we felt a little
bit revolutionary ideas even in walor to
move things into the direction of more
inclusiveness
more
um modern approaches to the world and so
she decided to accept this little boy
who was born without arms and legs with
just one little stump on one side of his
trunk um that he could move and use to
hold things and of course he was using
his mouth and teeth and beautiful face
um
to to write and do as much as he could
possibly do with those limitations and
he taught himself to hop walk on his
stumps
um so he was very fit and would actually
join into games and you know instead of
catching a b he would just hit it with
his head and the beauty is
that when we have that kind of
integration and when we teach a child he
was adopted into a family that had
adopted a bunch of kind of discarded
children as as horrible as that sounds
right
children who the parents didn't know
what to do with and
and yanis was one of these children and
his mother was very very
encouraging his adoptive mother so and
she did not do everything for him she
encouraged him very much to do as much
as he could with this little stump
and the whole school loved yanis of
course there were other children as well
because the original approach of walr is
to be integrated
of the entire spectrum of
society
um so that you know then when he had his
next electric wheelchair you know kids
would compete to ride with him and so
forth but the
integration and the
meaningfulness of somebody who
impairments that require others to
community to come closer together it
encourages the entire whatever group or
community that person is in to
collaborate
to make sure the other person is catered
to
um said good old saying do unto others
as you want done to yourself right so it
encourages that whole dynamic into a
direction that is a lot
more humanitarian and human and fun um I
remember there was always a lot of
laughter around
yenis and then as an adult now he's now
probably in his
30s um he's he has managed to travel
around the globe because one of his
goals was to travel and see other
countries and he would have um friends
helping
him um I'm sure all of this was financed
also by he he would always have somebody
filming his ex Expeditions into the
world so he's been on
Mount M map Pichu what's the name now
he's been on on mountains and he's swam
oceans and he's done everything
without arms and legs so just to close
that out and the books by yanis with a J
so we would probably say Janice but it's
pronounced because he grew up in Germany
um Janis
mcdavis um can be
found in in German and in
English so I just wanted to put that out
there he has of course there videos on
YouTube about him and interviews with
him and so forth he has become a real
personality um because he was not
letting it stop his being and his
incredible brain
to yeah the fact that he
was limited in his um physical
abilities and you know what I call in
this particular
Mastermind defects that we're born with
so my own defects are plenty too but
they seem so minute in comparison to
yanis right I I was born with a hole in
my heart I my toes don't curl so I have
really weak tissue I you know have my
liver doesn't function properly I had
fatty tissue tumors until I went raw and
again you know that's stopped um those
challenges to my liver and it started
being functioning fine
so we can of
course adjust to many of those
challenges by changing our lifestyle but
if we can't we can work with
those impediments or
defects almost as though they were tools
to get give us an opportunity to arrive
at more
greatness um so unfortunately we don't
have
many people with me on this Mastermind
but I wanted to ask Charlie who is still
with us I think whether she was born
with any defects that you want to report
about
quickly when I was a child at age four I
was shot with pesticides the government
were
pesticide all the area of
Iowa the Swedish Community but they were
doing it all over Iowa for the crops and
excuse me was that
DDT DDT yes and okay they gave us
a one of these
type of it looked like a can with about
a 24 inch tube and you had this
pesticide in there and they said you
don't want to have any bugs anywhere
well there are lots of bugs and those
are natural for organic okay you don't
want to have them they're harmful it's
so you supposed to shoot this all around
anybody they gave each child one of
those C
no but because I acted like an adult at
age four I started I was the oldest and
I took care of my brother and sister and
I made all the food my grandmother uh
just was so patient with me at age four
so I was doing food I even cut up a uh
stood at the coal sto stove at age four
and Def fro I mean def feathered the
chicken and C C it up in the par I stood
there for 2 hours and doing that and I
thought to myself oh I want to become a
surgeon or a doctor because I am calm
under this well I never told anyone but
I'm a uh I wanted to become a doctor but
never told what was father
Engineers what what effect what effect
did the what effect did the pesticides
have okay I became
paralyzed really yes and then I I I
passed
out uh well that's just part of it I
wanted to have a Girl Scout house in the
back we had a it was like a storehouse
when we moved in and our house still
stands there the Girl Scout house that I
created out there no longer there and I
spoke to the person that bought our
house
just
recently it's still there so what
happened what happened um did you ended
up in the
hospital the uh well I ended up passing
out and taken to the hospital in the
next town there was no doctor in our
town and uh my mother would come e shy
describe excuse me shley describe what
happened before you passed out what did
you what made you pass
out uh well every day I was working on
this uh Girl Scout house to have this
for others and I didn't ask others to
help me I was a person that was just I
could work
alone
and but how did that Charlie how did
that have to do with the
pesticide well I also Burning live
magazines live magazines out of the
storehouse we we never had live
magazines but this was when we bought
the house and had the storehouse so I
was burning these every single day for
one year plus I got
pesticides and then I kept saying I have
to finish this Grill SK house but I I
have to finish it I just kept working
and my mother was working on secret
thing for the World War II and my father
went off to work on the Alaskan
Highway and so I just was a person that
and took care Char Charley I all all we
want to know is why you passed out what
happened don't tell us all the other St
and I was getting the pesticide so both
both and I passed out finally after
working on this one year and then uh I
lay in the hospital and doctor I was
given antibiotics penicillin I it first
came out then and said you will never
walk
again if you could
imagine and what did the doctor think
what happened why you why you should
never walk
again well maybe you know at that time I
didn't know uh what even ping exactly
did
antibiotic uh so I was taking so much of
that I became allergic to
antibiotic and then they didn't practice
me to get out of bed and finally after
several weeks they said well you can go
home and you won't be going to school oh
what a because I loved school I was a
perfectionist love yes so how did you
get back on your feet well my mother
took me and just laid me on on the CL
help
outside to lay on the C I lay on the C
there every day that was from May until
September and I said I I want to every
day I looked over the this three that I
said I don't remember what time what
kind of tree that was and I would see
the cillar crawly Charli how did you get
back on your feet okay I kept saying to
my mother I want to walk and I want to
get the SCH well no phys therapy no no
and he says I said mother could you
please help me I had no walk or anything
I gave such things then and he says okay
I will help so when school was going to
he says I will help I will help you and
my brother will live too help me try to
walk I I can't I can't hear you very
well say that again help me try to walk
to school my brother and my mother but
mainly my mother my mother used to lift
me to the bath toilet to
go and then at school uh she placed the
C and I was to rest on the C and then
just get up uh no recess for me just lay
on the cart and and the kids did not
make fun of me there they're all
sweeties they did not but they didn't
wonderful they didn't help really just
didn't make fun of me and then I got up
uh uh to try to sit up and read and I
used to be a beautiful
reader gosh I was out of breath to read
and so then I be is there is there is
there by any chance did somebody call
this polio at the time well it could
have been too because my brother he he
oh the other thing the government gave
us was like 25 PBS of sugar you can't
eat oatmeal any longer that was about
the same time during the war no oatmeal
you have to eat
wheedies and these box cereals which had
sugar and you get your toy who cares
about the toy because I had no toys and
yeah so um for me for me to to make this
meaningful for this particular
Mastermind I would like to wrap this as
such so there is quite a bit of evidence
that what we call polio may have been
caused by DDT
exposure and
sugar okay and white bread white
everything a lack of vitamin A lack of B
vitamins because of course they are in
oats for example
and and um when you take the skin off of
grains you're
depriving whether it's rice or or wheat
or oats for that matter you're depriving
the body of the B vitamins so just to
wrap this up so this might be a good
example of how you were injured by the
chemical world and this was causing
paralysis and um yeah and of course
paralysis can go into the lungs as well
that's why you're out of breath all the
time when you try to sit up right or
walk so that makes a lot of
sense but today you are how old
charlee how old well
everybody until just a few years ago
they thought I was 16 they thought I was
16 because I do all this s grass and raw
greens and well uh I've aged I aged like
overnight taking care of my husband
Round the Clock age
I and people guess me like 65 but I'm
really
88 congratulations that's what I want to
hear shley is 88 and functioning and has
gone through these phases of raw food
and we've had several conversations and
I'm so happy to hear that you twoo were
able to overcome those physical
impediments in in your case you weren't
born with those impediments but they
were caused by toxicity coming in from
the outside right and I Fallen another
thing I have fallen uh let's see over
two years ago because of my eyesight it
I have wet macular degeneration I cannot
see in the light and the dark and I fell
two different times and I couldn't then
walk I had to go on a walker and I
overcame this because I said Wonder
overcome I am the body can regenerate
itself and overcome these physical
disabilities yeah
so today um the the focus is however on
defects we are born with that we cannot
change for example we're born with
um with
nasal cavities that are too narrow and
you know my my sister had that and you
know they have to be then surgically
broadened or you have to live with those
I have another friend who just always
talks like he has a cold but that's
because his his nostrils are too narrow
and he was born like that so there are
there are these kinds of defects that we
cannot change with the best lifestyle or
anything but that can challenge us
to perform in spite of or with those
impediments that do not really mean that
we have to stop our contribution to the
world so or sometimes we can even be
challenged to do more for others because
we
understand what it is like to have these
impediments to have these
limitations
so in in the to go a little bit more
into the why 21
days into many many lifechanging courses
also the one at hypocrates
Institute now hypoc is Wellness in
Florida um they have a life
transformation course that is three
weeks of course other people have four
weeks six weeks I also have a 12 month
program which helps you set up lifestyle
and possibly a business um so therefore
um I wanted to get to the shortest
possible time in which we can actually
change our approach to life and work
with what we have to the best of our
possibilities and we catch ourselves of
course again and again seling off and
making these excuses well you know my
heart or well you know you know I can't
because instead of
embracing that which we do have the
talents that we have and kind of
dragging the impediments along with us
and therefore making great
contributions to the world and I'm
always being so Grand to the world it
can just be to one other person like
Charley is saying you know she looked
after her husband for so long and that
intensity of um putting out energy to
help another person survive
longer is is very important as well
because it doesn't always have to be
hundreds or thousands of people that are
impacted by our actions it can be one
person it can be a family it can
be yeah it can be a group of animals in
in an animal sanctuary it can be so many
different things
so that's what I wanted to emphasize
that in 21 days changing our
routines can become
habit and changing our routines means
including things like deep breathing
like looking in in the mirror and saying
I love you I have another little ritual
that I do where I say I love you my
Planet I love you my sunshine I love you
all of humanity and I love you my body
so while that to some people may seem
silly it is actually when we're
consciously doing
it it is I suppose similar but in my
eyes better than prayer where we're
praying for somebody else to give us
something but we are saying I can love
and I can give and therefore I can
contribute um without having to beg for
somebody else to give something to me if
I have that attitude it actually
attracts others to also have that
attitude with me again giving my little
example here having to move out of the
house that I was renting because it was
going to get renovated and sold and
suddenly finding myself in the situation
where I had to buy another house and
this time I wanted to buy and not rent
um and succeeding in doing that with the
help of so many people and having this
transition in several of my friends
offering while you can stay with me you
can stay with me you can stay with me
and I opted for this Garden Cottage um
among Meadows and apple trees that I'm
not pesticide
treated um
so that I can
have others giving to me when I'm in the
mode of giving to
others
um that's I think the future where we
move away from competition and toward
contribution and understanding that the
entire world could be so much more
beautiful and
noning and non poverty creating if we
allowed ourselves to have that attitude
so it's the breathing it's the rest it's
the selflove and it's the giving and
it's the it's the exercise the
challenging our body to do things that
are a little hard
but getting into the routine and
understanding that if we go to sleep
without having done any
exercise we will feel not quite right so
therefore there's an exercise routine
that I recommend that I do on my bed so
even if I didn't get to going running or
doing other exercises my programs I can
still before going to sleep spend 10
minutes exercising on my bed bed and it
still is effective so creating that
routine of going through all these steps
another one of the steps is water you
want to drink really good water at least
half a gallon a day you know of course
most healing uh programs include a
gallon a day which for some people is
too much but yeah between half a gallon
and a gallon is a good amount of fresh
good spring water
or or optimally fil filtered
Waters um so that's also part of it
oxygen and another item that I have in
my 21 days program is to tell somebody
you love
them and luckily in today's world we can
tell our friends we love them we can
tell sometimes strangers we love them
right and it
again creates something in ourselves
that is physically by the way
provable endorphins get created when we
tell somebody I love
you it's a really beautiful thing you
know that there is a physical mirror of
what we mentally
emotionally put out into the world or
feel experience erience think even
everything has a
physical
reaction both ways right we can also
have a physical well-being that
translates into the emotional happiness
and vice
versa
so that's all part of the 21 days and 21
days on the best possible nutrition of
course therefore is also 21 days on Raw
Organic Raw plant
foods and yes some people will say well
I can throw in a raw egg couldn't I or I
could throw in a a raw slice of meat
and um yeah I had a client like that
recently
um who felt that she absolutely had to
have
um raw meat but because she
couldn't not
have it kicked everything else out of
whack
so allowing ourselves to start a new
chapter requires of course a certain
amount of commitment to ourselves and to
that which we decide to
do um so yeah 21 days is just three
weeks three moons that put us into a new
Rhythm you could also of course say you
know the moon cycle is 28 or 29 days
really
um
but it is within
that period that we
can come to terms with what we have and
put
out more of our own ability of our own
Talent
than we thought Poss than we thought
possible so that's what the 21 days on
Raw does and what the allowing ourselves
to live with our
limitations but using them as challenge
to catapult us forward into the purpose
that we can have and that we decide we
have and the purpose can change during
our lifetime you know we may have a
period where we're like in my case where
we're teaching a period where we're um
in entertainment a period where where
Etc where the focus is on different
areas and um it doesn't have to be one
streamlined purpose but for some it is
and that's perfectly fine
too all right
so um
what is your contribution to the world
how would you like to enhance that
contribution and if so what are you
willing to commit to to give you the
extra push into that
purpose if that is something that you
want to learn more
about communicate with me about the 21
days on Raw program it is short and then
of course you can transition into the
longer program or you can just have
followups but it allows us to in a small
group push ourselves into this next
level and the older we get yeah I just
wanted to add that too the older we get
of
course
the the more we think okay that's enough
already sometimes we
think we just don't have as much energy
as we had 20 30 years ago and we have
all these
limitations and those too can be taken
as factors to push us into a routine
that accommodates the fact that yes this
body is 70 years old it cannot do the
same as it did when it was 30 years old
but in some cases it can actually do
better I had never run a any kind of
race I ran my first 5k race at 64
because it was always oh no I can't my
heart my muscles are too weak my tissues
my
whatever I ran my first 5k at 64 and my
first half
marathon NOS what was it first 5k at 62
first half marathon at 64 that's how it
was and I don't know whether I'll do
another half marathon I keep thinking I
want to but I've have become slower I
have become very slow you know it's just
a trot
running that is not at the same
speed that I acquired in those
60s we'll see what the 70s will bring at
the moment I'm pushing so join me to
push for your extra
extra level next
level um shley would you like
to tell us what
your purpose now is that you
feel uh my perfect now
intervie perfect now is
to uh first thing I have usually is the
he Gra
juice then I have Dandy lion and some
greens that I don't take hail as such I
take parsley and
cilantro but I I love Dand lands they
are for the liver oh absolutely dandel
lands are marvelous but what do you feel
is your purpose in life now my purpose
talking about interviews
doing the
interviews and then writing the
interviews down and then they are going
to be part of my
Memoir yes yes and I knew nothing about
writing a memo I haven't really
researched that but it's to be
accountable accountable to write
something down after the interviews
about the person we get invited to do oh
the Polish the
Swedish uh church
activities Oh gosh it's
just it's so many interviews that is
challenging and then to get it written
down so this yes but that's so next is
to uh to encourage people to
eat uh to do just hard they start out
with a small step and then that builds
on the next step and they just keep
doing they don't have to be perfect you
do not I got over that several years ago
in teaching kids do not be perfect we're
not going to follow anybody else don't
compare yourself to anybody else I well
but yeah I I hear you but you still have
to take example of people who did it so
that you know that you have a path to
follow right yes yes well you are an
inspiration uh
Dr
uh oh hypocrates was it in
Dr I did 14 years of workshops here I
did three day workshops with uh Dr
Clement for 14 years three-day workshops
and then he would go back to
Florida and then I taught to I'll tell
you I taught at the dewi community
center last I was teaching in the garden
about organic and they closed down on
covid and I haven't been back since but
I worked 10 years there then I taught
kids before that every grade level and
so I still will do that uh I'll do
certain this yes get kids so that's what
what I wanted to hear Shirley it's
wonderful that at 88 you now can tell a
story of a lifetime how you made your
health last right you made your health
last and you showed so many others how
to do that and that's that's what I
wanted to hear so the purpose never ends
if we allow it to continue right yes if
you don't have to a challenge in your
life you have nothing to live for you
have to take on big challenges and this
makes you feel really energetic I going
to do this and I'm going to do my little
steps each day so I go
outside and because of my eyesight I had
challeng but I get up 24 times out of
the chair because most adults are
sitting here and they go on their
computer and they get Hunchback and they
can't get out of their chair so I go
outside yes cherries right now slowly
have one cherry and get up out of the
chair and up and down as straight as
possible and I have I stand in in like
superwoman superwoman I stand yes there
you go beautiful that's what I wanted to
hear so that's purpose right there by
the way I I call those little get up
from the chair exercises get up you know
today we're gonna do 50
getups yes yes and then you feel you get
the breathing and then you feel
energetic
and
breathing I did have yes so that's I am
so glad that you're on this on this
Mastermind and even though we we had I I
lost all those people because because
the the sound wouldn't work on my other
device but we have recorded this now and
we're going to close it out right here
and I'm really happy that we got to
experience an example of somebody who is
a bunch older than I am and is still on
purpose doing interviews and teaching
and and showing others how you can live
meaningfully and strong with the
limitations you've had and that you may
have
overcome um into a ripe age into a
beautiful wonderful 88 year long life
and Beyond you know shely is going to
hit the three figures I'm I'm pretty
sure about that now I did do uh monthly
seminars with other doctors and I always
prepared the food well this all stopped
during covid and I haven't and I did
paid workshops too paid
workshops of course I taught raw food
but I haven't uh done that now um yes
yes all right one of these days I'm
coming over there you're still in
California right I'm in uh yes I'm one
from the water we go or two blocks we
walk down see the Ducks and the
sun uh the Sun up there and the
clouds and the beautiful flowers on the
way smell nature and and see these ducks
go eat grass up on the little bit of
grassers on the beach there and they are
nibbling they come like 12 in a pack and
they nibble their green grass then they
groom
themselves yes they do that all right
Charley thank you so much for being here
everybody check out 21 days on Raw um I
don't know whether it's on my website
Johanna raw foods but I'm easy to find
just Google Prof Johanna Sophia or
Professor Johanna Sophia and and you
will find me and all kinds of
connections and possibilities of
studying with me learning with me and
starting your next chapter at that
elevated level at that purpose into your
next era and that's it for today bye bye
thank you thank you so much I love you
you look beautiful oh I love you too
shle yes oh I'm so glad you did that
let's say that every day you are getting
this new home and you're going to teach
yes I will I look forward to creating my
Edible Garden in my new home oh yes and
you can
tell Inspire others to have their own
little tiny garden out there absolutely
that's exactly what I'm going to do so M
MW MW
ciao bye bye a kiss for you